Okay
בוקר טוב, boker tov, right.
Today's דף daf is, well, officially כ"ט. chaf-tet. We pick up at
the very bottom of כ"ח עמוד א' chaf-chet amud aleph by the
two dots, about eight lines from the bottom.
Oh no, we actually did that. We pick up at the very
last line of כ"ח עמוד א'. chaf-chet amud aleph. So איסור מצוה.
issur mitzvah. So we're finishing up the משנה mishna that it was
with the four brothers and two of them died, married two sisters,
and then it's talking about if one of those is an ערוה,
ervah, though it solves the problems because then you don't have the
אחות זקוקתו achos zekukaso issue. But however, if one of them is
only an איסור מצוה issur mitzvah or an איסור קדושה issur kedusha
דרבנן derabbanan or only a לאו, lav, like for the for a
כהן, kohen, then that doesn't really get her out of the picture
because there's still a זיקה, zika, so you still have the same
issue, so you still have to do
חליצה. chalitza. The גמרא gemara says הנמי תנינא, hanami tanina, top of
כ"ח עמוד ב'. chaf-chet amud bet. We also taught this idea. איסור
מצוה איסור קדושה חולצת ולא מתייבמת. issur mitzvah issur kedusha choletzas velo
misyabemes. A woman who is אסור assur דרבנן derabbanan or אסור, assur,
for example, to a כהן, kohen, but it's not a real ערוה,
ervah, you do חליצה chalitza not יבום. yibum. So התם, hasam, איסור
מצוה לחודיה, issur mitzvah lechuda, that was a straight case, a simple
case, one brother dies and the woman is an איסור דרבנן issur
derabbanan or איסור כהונה. issur kehuna. הכא, hacha, איסור מצוה ואחותה, issur
mitzvah ve-achosah, here it was this more complex case, hybrid case,
of the case of the two sisters and then the remaining two
brothers and one of these two sisters was an איסור מצוה issur
mitzvah to one of the brothers.
סלקא דעתך אמינא ליקום איסור מצוה במקום איסור ערוה ותתייבם קמשמע לן.
salga da'atach amina leikum issur mitzvah bemakom issur ervah vesisyabbem kamashma lan.
So maybe I would think that, look, this whole case, to remind
you, oh my god, this what a mess in this page, but
to remind you the basic case we're dealing with here, right, the
simple case, by now this has become the simple case, the simple
case we're dealing with here, right, is you had ראובן Reuven and
שמעון, Shimon, right, married to רחל Rachel and לאה, Leah, they both
died. Now you've got, you know, יהודה Yehuda and לוי, Levi, לוי
Levi and יהודה, Yehuda, okay, so we've got basically these are sisters,
okay, but each one of them can't do יבום yibum or חליצה
chalitza because they have a זיקה zika to both, so every one
is אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukaso, right, that was the case of the
משנה. mishna. So the גמרא gemara says but if for example רחל
Rachel is an ערוה ervah to לוי, Levi, so then she's out,
so there's no זיקה zika that לוי Levi has to רחל, Rachel,
she's an ערוה, ervah, so לוי Levi can do יבום yibum with
לאה, Leah, okay, so that was the case, yes, right, because then
if רחל Rachel is his daughter let's say, so he has no
זיקה zika to her, no relation. So לאה Leah isn't the sister
of his זקוקה zekuka because רחל Rachel has no longer any connection
to לוי, Levi, I mean she has a strong connection, but she
has no זיקה, zika, no quasi marriage, right?
How could they be, if they're sisters,
how could one be a daughter and the other not? Different
mother, different father, same mother, right, exactly. Okay, so the question is
let's say however רחל Rachel is not לוי's Levi daughter, let's say
for example רחל Rachel is, I don't know, an איסור issur something
else to לוי, Levi, an איסור דרבנן, issur derabbanan, like, I forget
even what the איסור דרבנן issur derabbanan are, but okay, she's some
דרבנן derabbanan איסור issur to לוי. Levi. So can he now, the
גמרא gemara says, now in this case I might think let's let
him do יבום yibum with לאה, Leah, why? Because the whole problem
here was a דרבנן derabbanan problem of אחות זקוקה, achos zekuka, sister
of a זקוקה, zekuka, which is a
דרבנן derabbanan problem. רחל's Rachel never his wife, she's a quasi wife.
So maybe since it's the whole thing of a דרבנן derabbanan problem
of אחות זקוקה achos zekuka getting in the way of him being
able to do יבום, yibum, maybe if she's a דרבנן ערוה, derabbanan
ervah, that's enough to get the דרבנן derabbanan problem of אחות זקוקה,
achos zekuka, right, the whole thing is דרבנן derabbanan anyway, so let
a דרבנן ערוה derabbanan ervah status get her offline so he can
do יבום yibum with לאה. Leah. All right, so that's the possibility,
which is a reasonable idea. If we're living in דרבנן derabbanan world,
let a דרבנן ערוה derabbanan ervah solve a דרבנן derabbanan problem. So
the גמרא gemara says סלקא דעתך אמינא, salga da'atach amina, we learned
from the top, thank you so much Seth, סלקא דעתך אמינא ליקום
איסור מצוה במקום איסור ערוה, salga da'atach amina leikum issur mitzvah bemakom
issur ervah, let the איסור מצוה, issur mitzvah, the דרבנן derabbanan איסור,
issur, qualify as an איסור ערוה issur ervah for this דרבנן derabbanan
issue of אחות זקוקה, achos zekuka, ותתייבם, vesisyabbem, and let him then
do יבום yibum with לאה, Leah, קמשמע לן. kamashma lan. So the
גמרא gemara says ותתייבם, vesisyabbem, so no, let's say that, that's a
good idea.
כיון דמדאורייתא רמיא קמיה, keivan demide'oraisa ramya kamey, so no, since מדאורייתא
mide'oraisa
רחל Rachel still is an, he still has a זיקה zika to
רחל, Rachel, since even though דרבנן derabbanan she's an ערוה, ervah, מדאורייתא
mide'oraisa he still has a זיקה zika to her, so לוי Levi
is still אחות זקוקה. achos zekuka. Of course, that itself is a
דרבנן derabbanan problem. סלקא דעתך אמינא משום מצוה עבדי רבנן, salga da'atach
amina mishum mitzvah avdi rabbanan,
but maybe I would think that
because of the מצוה mitzvah the רבנן rabbanan would go ahead and
allow and allow him to go ahead and treat this as an
ערוה ervah even though מדאורייתא mide'oraisa she's a זקוקה, zekuka, this whole
problem is a דרבנן derabbanan problem, so why not go ahead and
treat her as an ערוה ervah to let him do יבום yibum
with לאה, Leah, קמשמע לן kamashma lan that we don't say that.
Okay. Okay, so okay so now so that's basically the answer. But
that was a reasonable הוה אמינא, Havah aminah, let a דרבנן D'Rabbanan
ערוה Ervah solve a דרבנן D'Rabbanan problem of אחות זקוקתו. Achos zekukaso.
Moving on in the משנה, Mishnah, היתה אחת מהן. Haysa achas mehen.
It says if one of them was, the last line in the
משנה Mishnah is one was a let me just remind myself what
the last line in the משנה Mishnah was. היתה אחת מהן זו
ערוה וזו ערוה. Haysa achas mehen zo ervah vezo ervah.
So רחל Rachel is לוי's Levi daughter, לאה Leah is יהודה's Yehuda
daughter, same idea except it's with both of them. So they each
do יבום Yibum with the other woman, okay? It removes the אחות
זקוקתו Achos zekukaso because you know he's his daughter so he gets
out of the picture he can do יבום Yibum with לאה, Leah,
she's his daughter so she's out of the picture for יהודה Yehuda
so he can do יבום Yibum with רחל. Rachel. So the גמרא
Gemara says, הא זו למה לי? Ha zu lama li? Why do
you need that next case? היינו הך, Hainu hach, it's the same
point like we said before except you're just doubling it. מה לי
חד מה לי תרי? Mah li chad mah li trei? What do
I care if you're saying this הלכה Halachah with one or with
two? If one of them is a ערוה Ervah he does יבום
Yibum with the other one. לא צריכא, Lo tzricha, I need to
say it. דיאשמעינן התם, De'ashmienan hasam, maybe if you just said in
the case of one משום דאיכא שני דמוכח. mishum de'ika sheni demuchach.
If לאה Leah if if you only have a case where רחל's
Rachel לאה's Leah daughter, so לוי's Levi daughter, so לוי Levi can
do יבום Yibum with לאה, Leah, so you might think you might
not realize that this is a case of ערוה Ervah and that
and that you'll say in general in such a case you can
do יבום. Yibum. But because you have יהודה, Yehuda, he makes it
clear, יהודה Yehuda we don't let do יבום Yibum with either. לוי
Levi we let do יבום Yibum with לאה. Leah. So the presence
of יהודה, Yehuda, the restrictions that we apply on יהודה Yehuda make
it clear that for לוי Levi it's a special case. So that
makes sense why we do it. דאיכא שני דמוכח. De'ika sheni demuchach.
אבל הכא דליכא שני דמוכח, Aval hacha delika sheni demuchach, here the
second guy doesn't prove anything because לאה Leah winds up doing יבום
Yibum with לוי Levi winds up doing it with לאה, Leah, יהודה
Yehuda winds up doing יבום Yibum with רחל. Rachel. So somebody will
look at that case and think that it's not a special case,
that the general rule is that in such a case you can
do יבום. Yibum. So since דליכא שני דמוכח, delika sheni demuchach,
אימא לא, eima lo, then I would say that we don't allow
it. ואי אשמעינן הכא, Ve'ee ashmienan hacha, if we just allowed the
case of where there's two ערוות Ervos and both brothers do יבום
Yibum with the other sister, אדרבה תרווייהו מוכחי אהדדי. aderaba tarvaihu mochi
ahadadi. I would say no, if anything, the fact that they're both
doing יבום Yibum with different women proves one another, that we only
allowed one to do יבום Yibum with one and the other to
do יבום Yibum with the other. So that makes it clear that
it's because there's an ערוה Ervah operating here. אבל אידך, Aval idach,
if it was just a case of one of them doing יבום
Yibum and the other not at all, לא, lo, I might say
that that doesn't is not self-evident enough what's going on. צריכא, Tzricha,
we need both cases. Fine, we won't belabor that point. זו היא
שאמרו, Zu hi she'amru, the last line of the משנה, Mishnah, okay?
Which says this is what they said. Now this is going to
remind you of a whole complicated discussion from way back at the
beginning. The last line said this is what the rabbis meant when
they said if you have a sister, אחותה כשהיא יבמתה, achosah kshe'hi
yevamtah, a sister who's a sister-in-law, if one of them is an
ערוה, Ervah, then the other one is או חולצת או מתייבמת. o
choletzes o misyabemes. Okay, so you got a sister that's a sister-in-law,
so if one's an ערוה, Ervah, then the other one they can
do חליצה Chalitzah or יבום Yibum too. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, זו היא למעוטי מאי? Zu hi lema'utei mai? What when it
says this is what they meant when they said, that sounds like
we're excluding some other case that doesn't fit into this rule. למעוטי
איסור מצוה לזה ואיסור מצוה לזה. Lema'utei issur mitzvah lazeh ve'issur mitzvah
lazeh.
So ah, to come to tell me that it's only in a
case where רחל's Rachel a real ערוה Ervah to לוי Levi and
לאה's Leah a real ערוה Ervah to יהודה. Yehuda. But let's say
they were both a דרבנן D'Rabbanan ערוה. Ervah. Now we already dealt
with that case, you might remember. We said it's a דרבנן D'Rabbanan
ערוה Ervah even though this whole problem is an איסור דרבנן issur
D'Rabbanan of אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukaso, a דרבנן D'Rabbanan ערוה Ervah doesn't
solve it. But the גמרא's Gemara going to say, but maybe I
would think if you had two דרבנן D'Rabbanan ערוות, Ervos, right? So
if this sister's an ערוה Ervah to him and this sister's an
ערוה Ervah to him, then maybe we'll let them do יבום Yibum
with the opposite ones. Why should that be better? So למעוטי איסור
מצוה לזה ואיסור מצוה לזה. lema'utei issur mitzvah lazeh ve'issur mitzvah lazeh.
הא זו למה לי? Ha zu lama li? Why do I need
that? היינו הך, Hainu hach, it's the same point that we don't
let the איסור ערוה דרבנן issur ervah D'Rabbanan solve the problem of
אחות זקוקתו. achos zekukaso. מה לי חד מה לי תרי? Mah li
chad mah li trei? What's the difference between one and two? No,
מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought כאילו אמינא אוקי איסור
מצוה במקום איסור ערוה, ke'ilu amina uki issur mitzvah bimkom issur ervah,
when does an איסור דרבנן issur D'Rabbanan not count as an איסור
ערוה issur ervah to solve the אחות זקוקתו achos zekukaso problem, היכא
דאיכא למגזר משום שני. heicha de'ika limgzar mishum sheni. Because we're only
allowing it to one brother and not the other. So therefore we'll
say oh, if we let this problem solve it for one brother,
the other brother's going to think you know he's all like like
he won't realize it's a special case because it's only a דרבנן
D'Rabbanan ערוה Ervah and he'll come to do it even without that.
אבל היכא דליכא למגזר משום שני,
Aval heicha delika limgzar
mishum sheni, when there's no problem about the second brother, because each
brother gets to marry one of the women, אימא להאי אוקמינהו איסור
מצוה במקום איסור ערוה ולהאי אוקמינהו איסור מצוה במקום איסור ערוה. eima
le'hai ukmina issur mitzvah bimkom issur ervah ule'hai ukmina issur mitzvah bimkom
issur ervah. For one brother the איסור דרבנן issur D'Rabbanan counts as
an ערוה Ervah and he can do יבום Yibum with the other
woman. And the same for the other brother. ויבמו, veyibmu, and let
them do יבום. Yibum. קמשמע לן Kamashma lan that they can't. Okay,
so we went through a
classic thing the גמרא Gemara says which is like its צריכותות. tzrichusos.
Why every case in the משנה Mishnah is needed. It's all basically
the same הלכה. halachah. and you know sometimes the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
might tell you just for parallel but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* likes
explaining why every line I might have thought that it might be
different. Okay but basically it was a pretty good הוה אמינא *hava
amina* that an ערוה ervah דרבנן d'rabonon *ervah derabbanan* would solve a
דרבנן d'rabonon *derabbanan* problem of אחות achose, זקוקה *achos zekukah* but that's
not the case. Now we get to a line that you might
have remembered fondly or otherwise from way from the beginning of the
מסכת *masechet* which is applying all the 15 עריות arayos *arayos* to
this case. Okay so let's take a look. I don't know if
you remember what I'm talking about but you'll remember soon enough. So
the
ברייתא *braisa* says like this. אמר רב יהודה Yehuda אמר רב *Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav* וכן תני רבי חייא *v'chen tani Rebbe Chiya*
which רבי חייא *Rebbe Chiya* taught וכולן *v'chulan* in all of the
15 עריות arayos *arayos* in the first משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* אני קורא
בהן האסורה לזה מותרת לזה ואחותה כשהיא יבמתה אוכלת או מתיבמת *Ani
korei bahen ha'asurah lizeh muteres lizeh v'achosah k'shehi yevimta ocheles o misyabemes*.
In all of the cases of the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* right because
basically what we said is in this case okay רחל Rachel *Rachel*
and לאה Leah *Leah* are sisters, ראובן Reuven *Reuven* and שמעון Shimon
*Shimon* both die. Okay you know what so you have רחל Rachel,
*Rachel* לאה Leah *Leah* here okay now we basically say and here's
לוי Levi *Levi* and יהודה Yehudah *Yehuda*.
So basically what we say is is that you have אחותה *achosah*
they're sisters and they're sisters-in-law okay that's the basic case is אחותה
כשהיא יבמתה *achosah k'shehi yevimta* okay because they're sisters who were married
to
brothers. And if one of them is an ערוה ervah, *ervah* if
she's an
ערוה Ervah. *ervah* to if לאה Leah *Leah* is an ערוה
ervah *ervah* to יהודה Yehudah *Yehuda* then he does יבום yibum, *yibum*
with רחל Rachel *Rachel*. And if רחל Rachel *Rachel*'s an ערוה ervah
*ervah* to לוי Levi, *Levi* then he does יבום yibum. *yibum* with
לאה Leah *Leah*. Okay so if they're both עריות arayos. *arayos* they
get to do יבום yibum *yibum* with the other ones. So the
question is what is a scenario where you have sisters and brothers
and it can be an ערוה ervah *ervah* to one without being
an ערוה ervah *ervah* to the other right? רחל Rachel *Rachel*'s an
ערוה ervah *ervah* to יהודה Yehudah, *Yehuda* but not to לוי Levi
*Levi*. רחל Rachel *Rachel*'s an ערוה ervah *ervah* to לוי Levi *Levi*
but not to יהודה Yehudah *Yehuda*. לאה Leah *Leah*'s whatever you see
I'm confusing myself but anyway they're עריות arayos *arayos* to one without
the others and they're sisters and brothers. What's the scenario? So the
statement is I can make this work with all 15 cases in
the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*, all 15 עריות arayos, *arayos*. Okay now let's
start with like an easy one okay an easy one would be
let's say mother-in-laws when it's on the wife's side. That's going to
be easy right because לאה Leah. *Leah* is יהודה Yehudah *Yehuda*'s wife's
mother but obviously has no relation to לוי Levi *Levi* and the
same רחל Rachel, *Rachel* is לוי Levi *Levi*'s wife's mother but no
relation to יהודה Yehudah? *Yehuda*. So there's a place where you could
apply one of the עריות arayos *arayos* and do both same ערוה
ervah *ervah* status to both women and they're sisters. רחל Rachel. *Rachel*
and לאה Leah?
*Leah* are sisters through their father.
Through well yes I mean yes in that case through their father
and there'll be other cases through their mother. Okay so you could
apply it to all of them and that it works that they're
the that they're sisters, they're both at the same level of ערוה
ervah. *ervah* but only to one of the brothers. Okay it's like
a little like you know mind teaser right like a puzzle let's
keep can we work it out with all the cases? So the
answer is we can וכולן אני קורא בהן האסורה לזה מותרת לזה
ואחותה כשהיא יבמתה אוכלת או מתיבמת *v'chulan ani korei bahen ha'asurah lizeh
muteres lizeh v'achosah k'shehi yevimta ocheles o misyabemes*. It can work with
all of them okay you can go ahead that's a homework assignment
for the reader. Okay ורב יהודה Yehudah, מתרגם מחמותו ואילך *v'Rav Yehuda
metargem mechamoso va'eilach*. But רב יהודה Yehudah *Rav Yehuda* says
no I'm only going to say that by the list in the
משנה Mishnah: *Mishnah* that starts with mother-in-law. That's the case I gave
you that was an easy case. אבל שית בבי דרישא *aval sheis
bavi d'reisha* the first six עריות arayos *arayos* לא lo, *lo* he
doesn't want to apply to this case. If you remember the first
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* the first six עריות arayos *arayos* were all derivations
of daughter. It was your daughter
your granddaughter right what is it to go back way to the
beginning of the first משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*? Okay בתו בת בתו בת
בנו בת אשתו ishto, בת בנו ובת בתו *Bito bas bito bas
beno bas ishto bas beno bas bito*. Your daughter your granddaughter in
two ways she could be your granddaughter that's three, your wife's daughter
who's not yours and your wife's granddaughter also two variations of that
right through the son through the daughter that's six. Those we don't
teach. Why? We don't apply to this case because the case of
daughter let's figure out the case of daughter. רחל Rachel
*Rachel* is לוי Levi *Levi*'s daughter. How could רחל Rachel, *Rachel* be
לוי Levi, *Levi*'s so רחל Rachel *Rachel*'s לוי Levi. *Levi*'s
daughter but not יהודה Yehudah *Yehuda*'s daughter. How is that possible that
it's לוי Levi *Levi*'s daughter without being יהודה Yehudah *Yehuda*'s daughter?
How can that be possible?
I'm sorry not that right right of course that's possible. How could
they be sisters? I'm sorry. How could
רחל Rachel *Rachel* and לאה Leah *Leah* thank you how could רחל
Rachel *Rachel* and לאה Leah, *Leah* be sisters and רחל Rachel *Rachel*
is daughter and לאה Leah. *Leah* is not? So they have a
different mother okay fine. So here's a mother will be חנה Chana
*Chana* and here's a mother will be דבורה Devorah *Devorah* okay so
that's her mother and that's her mother fine okay so that's the
case of
daughter okay. Hold
on,
now I'm confusing myself. One minute. That's a daughter,
sister not his
daughter. Wait a minute.
Hold
on, now I'm confusing myself. One second.
They had to have the same mother. They had to have the
same
mother.
I got it.
No, yeah, they had to have the same mother because it's two
different...
yeah, yeah, I got it wrong. You're right. That's the point. Same
mother, not a different mother. Different father, right? Same mother. No?
Yes! This... right, רחל's Rachel daughter and לאה Leah is not his
daughter, but they're sisters. Right, so they have the same mother. Thank
you. Okay, that's the point. They have the same mother, okay? They
both have the same mother, but they've got a different father, okay?
Now here's the problem. If they have... thank you, that was the
problem. Okay, so they're sisters. They've got the same mother. She's his
daughter, or she's the daughter from another man. Fine. Everything is wonderful.
Except that if רחל Rachel is his
daughter and חנה Chana. was his wife, then לאה Leah. is his
wife's
daughter. So she's also אסור assur to him, right? Okay, is that
clear? Yeah? So the only way this will work, that they have
the same mother and לאה Leah, is not his wife's daughter is
if he was never married to
חנה. Chana Got it? So חנה Chana was the woman he slept
with and they had רחל, Rachel but they were never married. And
then לאה Leah is a daughter חנה Chana. had with another man.
So they're sisters, but לאה Leah. is not his wife's daughter because
he was never married to חנה. Chana. So we don't want... so
he says, I don't want to talk about that case of daughter
because I don't want to talk about a scenario where it only
came through an איסור, issur, through an out-of-marriage child. Okay? And since
I don't want to talk about the daughter in that case, I'm
going to eliminate
the whole first six cases of the משנה Mishnah because they're all
in the daughter category. Daughter, granddaughter, wife's daughter, wife's granddaughter. Although the
only one that requires saying they weren't married was the case with
חנה. Chana.
What if he divorced her?
That wouldn't matter. She'd still be prohibited.
Yeah, exactly. Exactly. So if she was ever his wife, the prohibition
remains. Okay, but good question. So he says, ורבי יהודה מתרגם מחמותו
ואילך. v'Rabbi Yehuda metargem meichamosto va'eilech. I only want to apply the
list from mother-in-law down. אבל שיתא בבי דרישא, aval sheisha bavi d'reisha,
the first six, which are daughter and granddaughter and wife's daughter, wife's
granddaughter, לא, lo, I don't want to talk about it. I don't
want to say that it applies to our case. מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? כיון דבתה באונסין הוא דמשכחת לה. keivan de'bita ba'onsin hu d'mishkachat
lah. The case of daughter would only work if it's a daughter
through, again, the גמרא Gemara whenever it discusses out-of-wedlock, for some reason,
does not say מפותה, mifuta, which means seduced or whatever, just you
know, a consensual sex, it always talks about אונסין, onsin, which is
rape, which I don't know why the גמרא Gemara always does that,
but anyway, since the only way you have that case of sisters
and one is forbidden to you and the other is not is
a case of a child, a daughter that was born out-of-wedlock, באונסין
הוא דמשכחת לה, ba'onsin hu d'mishkachat lah, בנישואין לא משכחת לה, benisuin
lo mishkachat lah, not through marriage. בנישואין קא מיירי באונסין לא קא
מיירי. benisuin ka'ma'eiba ba'onsin lo ka'ma'eiba. I want to say that the
scenarios we're talking about of these עריות or whatever are things that
came through children born within marriage, not children born outside of marriage.
ואביי מתרגם אף בתה מאנוסתו. v'Abayei metargem af bita d'meianusatah. And אביי
Abaye says, no, we'll apply all 15 cases can apply to this,
even the case of daughter, even though that
only works in a case when born out-of-wedlock. כיון דאשכחן משכחת לה.
keivan de'ashkachei mishkachat lah.
Since you have the scenario, אי באונסין תיהוי אי בנישואין תיהוי. ei
ba'onsin teihavei ei benisuin teihavei. So fine, if it'll be through out-of-wedlock,
literally rape, or within wedlock, either way though, we can apply all
15 עריות that will work in this case that you could have
cases of, again, it's like really is like a fun puzzle if
this is where you get your fun. I had a teacher who
once said to me, this is what they did before they had
TV.
So how can you get all 15 cases that they're sisters that
are the same ערוה ervah. to each brother but they're not, but
it's only to
one brother is an ערוה, ervah not this, and this one is
the same to the other one. So anyway, with the daughter it
only works if it is באונסין ba'onsin and he's saying I'm willing
to say that and we should apply all 15 cases to this
scenario, all 15 עריות. Okay. אבל אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, aval
eishet achiv shelo hayah b'olamo,
but here's the one case אביי Abaye says I don't want to
say applies to this case,
your brother's wife when you had not yet been born, אשת אחיו
שלא היה בעולמו, eishet achiv shelo hayah b'olamo, you might remember that.
כיון, keivan, in that case, אבל שלא היה בעולמו לא. aval shelo
hayah b'olamo lo. כיון דאליבא דרבי שמעון הוא דמשכחת
לה, keivan de'aliba d'Rabbi Shimon hu d'mishkachat lah, because that will only
work according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אליבא דרבנן לא משכחת לה,
aliba d'Rabbanan lo mishkachat lah, and it won't work according to the
רבנן. Rabbanan. בפלוגתא לא קא מיירי. biflugeta lo ka'mira. I don't want
to say we're talking about a case that's... that's open for debate.
So to get it that each wife is אשת אחיו שלא היה
בעולמו eishes achiv shelo haya beolamo to the other brother will only
work according to רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. I will explain what this
means in a minute, the גמרא Gemara. will explain it whatever and
then I'll explain the גמרא. Gemara רב ספרא מתרגם אף אשת אחיו
שלא היה בעולמו. Rav Safra metargem af eishes achiv shelo haya beolamo.
רב ספרא Rav Safra says it applies even in that case ומשכחת
לה בשישה אחי u'mishkachas la b'shisha achei
and you can get it with six brothers ואליבא דרבי שמעון v'aliba
d'Rebbe Shimon and according to רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon וסימנך v'simonoch and
here's the case: מת נולד ויבם, מת נולד ויבם. meis nolad v'yibem,
meis nolad v'yibem. Okay, so died, born, and did יבום, yibum died,
born, and did יבום. yibum Now the גמרא Gemara is going to
spell it out for once. ראובן ושמעון נשואים שתי אחיות. Reuven u'Shimon
nesuim shtei achayos. ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon, married to two sisters,
like we say, okay?
ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon but we're going to do it this
way, make it a little bit, I hope, easier,
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon married to רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah
Now this is a case of אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. eishes
achiv shelo haya beolamo. Remember means that one of the brothers has
to die and then the other brother has to be born, right,
that he was born after, right, when the, you know, when the,
after the other brother had already died, okay, after
that they were not both alive at the same time, the woman
that's now going to would have been in the מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibum. was never married to his brother when he and his
brother were alive at the same time. Okay, so here's the case.
Okay, ראובן ושמעון נשואים שתי אחיות, לוי ויהודה נשואים שתי נוכריות. Reuven
u'Shimon nesuim shtei achayos, Levi v'Yehuda nesuim shtei nochriyos. לוי Levi, and
יהודה Yehudah are married to, this does not mean non-Jewish women, it
means unrelated to anybody else, so they're married to דבורה Devorah and
חנה. Channah Okay, wonderful. שתי נוכריות. shtei nochriyos.
Now,
מת ראובן נולד יששכר. meis Reuven nolad Yissachar.
So ראובן Reuven has died and then יששכר Yissachar is born. So
now, okay, that's step one, that's step two. יששכר Yissachar is born.
Now רחל Rachel? to יששכר Yissachar is since he was born after
ראובן Reuven, died, רחל Rachel, was already widowed, he was never alive
at the same time for ראובן, Reuven so רחל Rachel now is
אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. eishes achiv shelo haya beolamo.
Right?
Yes? Everybody understand that? Okay, so that's what happened. אשת אחיו שלא
היה בעולמו. eishes achiv shelo haya beolamo. Okay, so that's מת
נולד meis nolad and then... מת ראובן נולד יששכר ויבם
לוי.
meis Reuven nolad
Yissachar v'yibem Levi.
Now לוי, Levi step number three, does יבום yibbum, with רחל, Rachel.
okay?
So מת נולד ויבם. meis nolad v'yibem. One, two, three.
Okay, maybe we'll make it easier, we won't put לוי Levi up
here, we'll put it down here.
מת נולד meis nolad and then לוי Levi, comes and he was
already married to דבורה and he did יבום yibbum with
רחל. Rachel Okay, מת נולד ויבם. meis nolad v'yibem. Okay, and רחל
Rachel to
יששכר Yissachar is still אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, eishes achiv shelo
haya beolamo, okay?
Right? She's still an ערווה, ervah, okay?
מת נולד ויבם. meis nolad v'yibem. Okay. Now,
זבולון Zevulun isn't born yet. By the time, just to jump ahead
for a second, by the time זבולון Zevulun is going to be
born, לוי Levi. is already married to רחל, Rachel. right? So when
זבולון Zevulun is born, רחל Rachel, is not an ערווה ervah to
זבולון. Zevulun. You got that? Right? רחל Rachel remained an ערווה, ervah,
רחל Rachel became an ערווה ervah to לוי Levi right here... wait,
wait, wait, she is an
ערווה... ervah... רחל Rachel. became an ערווה ervah to
יששכר! Yissachar! Sorry.
רחל Rachel. was an ערווה ervah to יששכר, Yissachar, right, at stage
number two. She remains an ערווה ervah to יששכר Yissachar even after
לוי did יבום. yibbum So this is an איסור issur of אשת
אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eishes achiv shelo haya beolamo that he has
to her. The idea is to get it with one brother and
not the other. When זבולון Zevulun is going to be born, רחל
Rachel is already married to לוי, so רחל Rachel is not going
to be an ערווה ervah to זבולון. Zevulun. So this is a
case where רחל Rachel. is an ערווה ervah to יששכר Yissachar because
she became an ערווה ervah at stage two,
right, when he was born and she was the free, and now
she remains an ערווה ervah to him, but she won't be an
ערווה ervah to זבולון. Zevulun. That was
the
debate before. That was according to רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. Very good,
you remember that. Okay, now, okay, that's stage number one. מת ראובן
נולד יששכר ויבם לוי. meis Reuven nolad Yissachar v'yibem Levi. מת שמעון,
meis Shimon, now on this side of the board, okay,
we've got שמעון Shimon dies
here now, we'll call that four, that's מת, meis, מת שמעון, meis
Shimon,
נולד זבולון, nolad Zevulun, stage number five is going to be נולד,
nolad, okay, זבולון Zevulun is now born. Now right now זבולון Zevulun
is born. What's his relationship to רחל? Rachel מותר, Muttar, right? Non-problematic.
She's already married to לוי. What's his relationship to לאה? Leah. ערוה.
erva This is אשת אחיו, Eishes Achiv, אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו.
Eishes Achiv she-lo hayah be-olamo. Okay. What's לאה Leah. status, by the
way, to יששכר? Yissachar? מותר. Muttar. מותר Muttar because שמעון Shimon died,
there's a מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibbum? he even has with לאה,
Leah right? He and יהודה Yehudah, were around at the same time.
So here she's ערוה erva to זבולון Zevulun but not ערוה erva
to יששכר Yissachar as opposed to רחל, Rachel which is ערוה erva
to יששכר Yissachar but not ערוה to זבולון. Zevulun. Okay, מת, meis,
נולד, nolad, then ויבם, ve-yibbem, that's now יהודה Yehudah now does יבום
yibbum with—who's married to חנה—now Channah does יבום yibbum with לאה. Leah
So לאה Leah, now is—so now we've got a case of two
brothers, לוי and יהודה, Yehuda. they both die. יששכר Yissachar cannot—is רחל
Rachel. is an ערוה יששכר, Yissachar, אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, Eishes
Achiv she-lo hayah be-olamo, but not with לאה. Leah And the flip,
זבולון Zevulun is an ערוה with לאה, Leah but not with רחל.
Rachel. So that's how you can have two sisters that are אשת
אחיו שלא היה בעולמו Eishes Achiv she-lo hayah be-olamo that are מותר
muttar to the other brothers, to the alternate brothers. Okay. מת שמעון
נולד זבולון ויבם מותרת לזה ואסורה לזה. Meis Shimon nolad Zevulun ve-yibbem
muteseres le-zeh va-asurah le-zeh. Okay, מת לוי ויהודה ויבם יהודה. Meis Levi
ve-Yehudah ve-yibbem Yehudah. מתו לוי ויהודה בלא בנים ונפלו לקמי יששכר וזבולון
האסורה לזה מותרת לזה ואסורה לזה מותרת לזה וחוזרת כשיבמתה. Meisu Levi
ve-Yehudah belo vanim ve-naflu lekamei Yissachar ve-Zevulun, asurah le-zeh muteseres le-zeh va-asurah
le-zeh muteseres le-zeh ve-chozeres keshivyemta. Okay.
So you have all the—you have the whole thing. Now the point
is, as was correctly pointed out, this only works according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, which is why we said this is only רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon because according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, the רבנן Rabbanan
would say that even though when זבולון Zevulun was born, רחל Rachel
was already married to לוי, she's still an ערוה to זבולון Zevulun
because he was—because her status—because she was still שלא היה בעולמו lo
hayah be-olamo even though when he comes in he has a new
relationship, her relationship vis-a-vis ראובן Reuven still remains and therefore she remains
an ערוה. So that's why it said it only worked according to
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it's only because of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
is רחל Rachel. okay since she was already married to לוי by
the time זבולון Zevulun was born. Okay, לא, let's get to the
משנה. Mishnah, Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says now, למה
לי יבם יהודה?
lamah li
yibbem Yehudah? Why do I need יהודה in this mix? בלא יבם
יהודה נמי משכחת לה. Belo yibbem Yehudah nami mishkachas lah. Without יהודה
you could also figure it out. Okay, now this is getting so
complicated. Okay, but how do you figure it out without יהודה? Because
without יהודה, says look, why did we need יהודה in this whole
thing and יהודה to come here and do יבום? yibum, Let's say
there was no יהודה here, right? שמעון Shimon. died, okay, and let
the two people that died be לוי and שמעון. Shimon Okay. שמעון
Shimon was married to רחל. Rachel זבולון Zevulun was born. שמעון Shimon
died, then זבולון Zevulun was born. Now you have it, right?
יששכר Yissachar can do יבום yibum with לאה Leah and not with
רחל, Rachel and זבולון Zevulun can do יבום yibum with רחל Rachel
and not with לאה. Leah Why did you need to get another
person in there to be married to another wife to take them
out and you have the same scenario? These two are brothers, שמעון
Shimon and לוי, and so the thing works out. So the גמרא
Gemara says, why do you need it? So the גמרא Gemara says,
משום צרה. mishum tzarah. Because we wanted to have a case not
just of the ערוות, ervas, but the צרת ערוה tzaras ervah as
well. So in this case, okay, you could have a case of—with
יהודה in it, you could have a case also of the צרת
ערוה tzaras ervah which if it was just שמעון Shimon... you wouldn't
have because if she had a co-wife, the co-wife would also be
אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו Eishes Achiv she-lo hayah be-olamo to זבולון.
Zevulun. So I don't know if you're still with me here, but
if you want to get—anyway, if he was married to both, if
you took out יהודה, then they'd both be ערוה. But in this
case, only לאה Leah is an ערוה and חנה is only a
צרת ערוה. tzaras ervah. So we want to get a case also
of צרת ערוה tzaras ervah so we need to have יהודה in
the mix. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
התינח צרה hateinach tzarah fine, so you want to have a case
where this applies also to צרת ערוה, tzaras ervah, but צרה דצרה
מאי איכא למימר? tzarah de-tzarah mai ika lemeimar? Remember the first משנה
said fifteen women and their צרות tzaras and צרות צרותיהן. tzaros tzaroseihen.
So could you have this case of like the criss-crossing, you know,
whatever, with a case of אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו Eishes Achiv
she-lo hayah be-olamo and the צרת צרה tzaras tzarah of it? So
how are you going to get it? So the גמרא Gemara. says,
okay,
כגון דהדר ויבמו kigon de-hadar ve-yibbeimu נמי nami גד Gad ואשר. Asher.
Throw in two more brothers גד Gad and אשר, Asher, I'll let
you figure that out. But okay, we can work that one out
too. Fine. I think that's enough of that. Let's get on now
to the next משנה.
All right. So the משנה: שלשה אחים שנים מהם נשואים שתי אחיות.
Sheloshah achim shenayim meihem nesuim shtei achayos. Three brothers, two of them
are married to two sisters. Does that sound familiar? או אשה ובתה
או אשה ובת בתה או אשה ובת בנה. O ishah u-vittah o
ishah u-vas bittah o ishah u-vas binnah. Any type of relationship. This
is just really the case we had before except it's taking the
four into three and telling us also that it could apply even
whatever type of relationship these two women have that are עריות to
one another.
Didn't we have like a sentence before, a couple of sentences back
that said why did you choose
four, you could have... Right.
So here the bigger point is just to tell us that it
applies to other עריות, again not much of a חידוש. chiddish. The
real חידוש chiddish here is to get to רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon.
או אשה בת בנה, o isha bas bnah, הרי אלו חולצות ולא
מתייבמות. harei eilu choltzos v'lo misyabmos.
No big חידוש chiddish there when you have this case of אחות
זקוקתו, achose zekukaso, or אם זקוקתו, im zekukaso, or בת זקוקתו, bas
zekukaso, or all the other types of relationships where you can't be
married to both, then you have to do חליצה chalitzah because of
the idea of זיקה. zika. רבי שמעון פוטר, Rebbi Shimon poter, but
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon actually says you can, although until now we've
all been saying it's a דרבנן d'rabbanan case and דאורייתא d'oraisa really
you should do יבום, yibum, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon goes to the
opposite extreme and he says you can just walk away because of
this idea that you can't marry both, you're even exempt from חליצה.
chalitzah. It's like a complete ערוה case. You just walk away, which
is a shocker. We'll see what that's based on in the גמרא.
Gemara היתה אחת מהן אסורה עליו איסור ערוה, haysa achas meihen asura
alav issur erva, אסורה בו מותרת באחותה. asura bo muteres b'achosa.
Now we're just repeating what we said before. Even if it's not
a case of sisters, mother and daughter, whatever it is, if one
of them is already forbidden to you, then there's no זיקה zika
and then you can go ahead and do יבום yibum, with the
other. איסור מצוה ואיסור קדושה, issur mitzvah v'issur kedusha, if it's only
an איסור דרבנן issur d'rabonon or like an איסור לאו, issur lav,
then חולצות ולא מתייבמות, choltzos v'lo misyabmos, then there still is an
idea of זיקה zika and you still have to do חליצה chalitzah
with both. So the big חידוש chiddish here is besides that it
applies to other עריות which is not much of a חידוש, chiddish,
is רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. So the גמרא gemara says תנו רבנן,
tanu rabanan, רבי שמעון פוטר בשתיהן מן החליצה ומן היבום. Rebbi Shimon
poter bishteihen min hachalitzah umin hayibum. In this case you get them
both off, even though it's only like a זיקה. zika. What's the
reason? שנאמר ואשה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור, shene'emar v'isha el achosa
lo tikach litzror, do not take a woman with her sister to
rub against one another, to create friction. בשעה שנעשו צרות זו לזו,
besha'ah sena'asu tzaros zu l'zu, when the women become co-wives, and here
it doesn't even mean co-wives,
co-sisters-in-law, both women now have a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum to
them from different brothers. They're considered to be co-sisters-in-law, co-wives, right? Because
they're like both as it were competing, I don't know, competing, but
anyway both potentially your wives. Okay, co-sisters-in-law. So זו לזו לא יהא
לכם אפילו באחת מהן, zu l'zu lo yiheh lachem afilu b'achas meihen,
you can't, there
is no concept of marriage even with one of them. So he
says this idea of
אחות זקוקתו, achose zekukaso, אחות, achas about אם זקוקתו, im zekukaso, בת
זקוקתו, bas zekukaso, all these things, he says that's a דאורייתא. d'oraisa.
When your relationship to these two is, were the זיקה zika sort
of turned into קידושין, kiddushin, it would be אסור assur because you
have two sisters or mother and daughter, whatever, then the whole thing
there's no זיקה zika at all in any part of it. So
that's a real extreme idea, which gives weight to the זיקה zika
or whatever, certainly learns it from a פסוק pasuk that there's not
even a מצוה mitzvah of חליצה, chalitzah, there's nothing. היתה מאחת מהן,
haysa mei'achas meihen,
if one is an ערוה you go ahead and you do it
with the other. הא תו למה לי, ha tu lama li, היינו
הך? hainu hach? Why are you telling me this? We've already taught
this. רבי שמעון אצריכה, Rebbi Shimon itzricha, you need it for רבי
שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salaka daitach amina, הואיל ואמר רבי
שמעון שתי אחיות לא חולצות ולא מתייבמות, hoil v'amar Rebbi Shimon shtei
achayos lo choltzos v'lo misyabmos, since he says if you have two
sisters you don't do חליצה chalitzah or יבום, yibum, לגזור משום שתי
אחיות דעלמא, ligzor mishum shtei achayos d'alma,
I might think that in this case where one of them is
forbidden to you and we let you do יבום, yibum you might
say no, we shouldn't let you do יבום yibum, with the other.
Since he says that normally in a case of two sisters you
have to completely walk away, maybe if we let you do יבום,
yibum right, for him it's more problematic, it's really a דאורייתא. d'oraisa.
What would happen for him in this case where you had the
two sisters from the two brothers and you went ahead and you
did יבום yibum with one of the sisters? So according to the
rabbis you'd be over on this איסור דרבנן issur d'rabonon of אחות
זקוקתו. achose zekukaso. According to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon what would you
have done? You would have done the איסור ערוה issur erva of
your brother's wife. Since he says that דאורייתא d'oraisa in that case
there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum then the women become the
real איסור דאורייתא issur d'oraisa of אשת אחיו, ashis achiv, right? So
for him it's very, very weighty if you would actually go ahead
and do יבום yibum in this scenario. So maybe because of that,
even when a case of יבום yibum would be allowed, like one
of the women is an ערוה to you and she's off the
table, maybe we shouldn't allow יבום yibum for the other woman because
that will actually might accidentally lead you to doing יבום yibum. in
a normal case like this. Normal? Anyway, in a case like this,
and that would be a real weighty איסור issur according to רבי
שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. So קמשמע לן kamashmalan that we're not going to
be concerned. Okay, is that clear why it's more weightier for רבי
שמעון? Rebbi Shimon? Right? According to the rabbis this is all a
דרבנן d'rabbanan problem of אחות זקוקתו. achose zekukaso. According to רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon דאורייתא d'oraisa there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum and
as soon as there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum דאורייתא, d'oraisa,
it's an איסור ערוה issur erva of אשת אחיו. ashis achiv. So
therefore maybe I would make more of a גזירה gezeirah and not
even allow this case where one of them is off the table,
קמשמע לן kamashmalan that we do allow it. איסור מצוה, issur mitzvah,
if it's an איסור מצוה issur mitzvah however you do חליצה, chalitzah,
not יבום. yibum, So now we've got a problem. According to רבי
שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, we're assuming that this is saying even according to
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon because the whole חידוש chiddish of this משנה
is רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. So why when the case of an
איסור מצוה issur mitzvah does רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon demand that you
do חליצה chalitzah even when there's no עריות here? It's just a
case of two sisters. He says you don't do חליצה. chalitzah. Why
when one is also another איסור דרבנן issur d'rabonon are you going
to do חליצה? chalitzah? והאמר רבי שמעון שתי אחיות לא חולצות ולא
מתייבמות. v'ha'amar Rebbi Shimon shtei achayos lo choltzos v'lo misyabmos. So why
here now because one of them is an איסור דרבנן issur d'rabonon
do you do חליצה? chalitzah? אמר גזירה משום איסור מצוה דעלמא. amar
gezeirah mishum issur mitzvah d'alma.
He says no, because here's the problem. If it was just a
case of two sisters... sisters and you walked away, people would understand,
oh, why did he walk away? Because it was two sisters, this
is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, okay fine, whatever. But if one of
them is also let's say, I don't know, let's say a גרושה
grushah to a כהן, kohein, right? And now you walk away, people
will say "Oh, you know why he walked away?
Because a גרושה grushah to a כהן kohein you don't have to
do חליצה," chalitzah, and they'll come to assume that in a normal
case an איסור מצוה issur mitzvah or איסור קדושה issur kedushah doesn't
need חליצה chalitzah because they'll focus on the fact not that her
other sister-in-law was her sister, they'll just look at this woman, they'll
say she was a גרושה, grushah, he was a כהן, kohein, "Hey,
did you hear what happened? So-and-so brother died and she was a
גרושה grushah and a כהן kohein and he didn't do חליצה." chalitzah.
So it must be that you don't have to do חליצה chalitzah
even by this איסור, issur, even by the איסור לאו issur lav
and even by an איסור דרבנן, issur d'rabbanan, and that's what they'll
focus on and not the fact that there was a sister, that
the sister-in-law was also the sister. Okay, so you understand it by
having this other fact, it makes people focus on that fact and
therefore and think that that because of that is why there wasn't
חליצה. chalitzah. So איסור מצוה דעלמא. issur mitzvah d'alma. התינח היא, Hateinach
hee, so fine, I get why you do חליצה chalitzah to the
one that was let's say the גרושה grushah to the כהן kohein
so people shouldn't think that in a normal case a גרושה grushah
to a כהן kohein doesn't need חליצה. chalitzah. אחותה מאי איכא למימר?
Achosa mai ika l'meimar? But why do you have to have the
sister get a חליצה? chalitzah? Just do a חליצה chalitzah to her.
גזירה אחותה משום לחודידה. Gezeira achosa mishum lachudidah. Fine, because we make
the sister get חליצה chalitzah since we're making her get
חליצה. chalitzah. אטו גבי ערוה לא גזרינן? Atu gabi ervah lo gazrinan?
But in a case where let's say it was really an איסור
ערוה issur ervah where one of the sisters was his daughter, we
wouldn't say, you know, like oh, the other one should get a
חליצה. chalitzah. So here too why do we make them both, why
do we make them get a חליצה? chalitzah? It's a pretty straightforward
answer: שאני ערוה דמיפרסמא למילתא Shani ervah d'mifarsma l'milsa וכולי עלמא ידעי.
v'chuli alma yadye. No, there it's clear. In a case where one
is a daughter, people like understand, she was a daughter, that's why
she didn't get חליצה chalitzah and they'll sort of understand that that's
why everything was happening. But in this
case where it was all just an איסור דרבנן, issur d'rabbanan, again,
it'll lead to this type of a confusion. So therefore we will
demand that there be a חליצה chalitzah A, so people don't think
an איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan you walk off without a חליצה, chalitzah,
and once we're doing one of them a חליצה, chalitzah, we're doing
the other a חליצה. chalitzah. All right, that was a little fast,
but I think you got it. משנה. השלשה
אחים.
Shlosha
achim. The basic again חידוש chiddush being that according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon in this case where the sister-in-laws are also עריות to
one another, whatever, that you couldn't be married to both, you do
it without יבום yibum and without חליצה. chalitzah. But maybe if there's
an איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan thrown in that ironically makes it worse
because people then will have wrong understandings of the איסור דרבנן issur
d'rabbanan and therefore we will demand חליצה. chalitzah. Okay. שלשה אחים, Shlosha
achim, three brothers. שנים נשואים שתי אחיות ואחד מופנה. Shnayim nesu'im shtei
achayos v'echad mufneh. Two are married to two sisters and one is
single, right? That's the right now פנוי, panuy, right? What? Nowadays in
modern Hebrew it's רווק, ravak, right, to be single, to be like
empty. It's interesting. It's the same word פנוי, panuy, unattached. Okay, so
anyway one is unattached. It's funny, beforehand it was also presumably one
was unattached but we weren't bothering to mention it. מת אחד מבעלי
האחיות ועשה בה מופנה מאמר. Meis echad miba'alei ha'achayos v'asah bah mufneh
ma'amar. Okay, now there's not, there's only three brothers.
Okay, now oh it's so easy now, only three brothers. Okay, only
three brothers and two sisters.
Okay.
So we've got
שמעון...
Shimon I know what I'm
saying... ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon married
to רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah. Okay, and here's לוי. Okay, so
one brother dies.
מת
אחד מבעלי האחיות ועשה בה
מופנה מאמר.
Meis echad miba'alei ha'achayos v'asah bah
mufneh ma'amar. And now he did מאמר ma'amar which is rabbinic קידושין
kiddushin with רחל. Rachel. Okay, now that was before שמעון Shimon died.
There was no problem of אחות זיקתו. achas zikaso. שמעון Shimon was
married to לאה. Leah He could have done יבום yibbum with
רחל. Rachel.
Okay, ואחר כך מת אחיו השני. V'achar kach meis achiv hasheini. And
then שמעון Shimon dies. So now is the question. If, okay, this
is step one, step two, step three. If this had been יבום,
yibbum, right, then לאה Leah would just walk away. אחות אשה, achas
isha, goodbye. But he didn't, he had מאמר ma'amar which is קידושין.
kiddushin. It started with זיקה zikah which is before he did anything,
plus מאמר. ma'amar. Is that strong enough to make רחל Rachel. like
his wife? This would have to work דאורייתא d'Oraisa if we're going
to let לאה Leah. walk away without חליצה. chalitzah. Would that be
strong enough to make רחל Rachel. like his wife that A, he
would be able to consummate it and do יבום yibbum, and we
wouldn't start worrying about
אחות זיקתו? achas zikaso? Forget לאה, Leah he's basically with רחל. Rachel,
So one stage would be do we allow him to do this
and ignore this דרבנן derabbanan of אחות זיקתו? achas zikaso? And the
other stage, that maybe could work
דרבנן derabbanan, since אחות Like enough דרבנן derabbanan. to ignore אחות זקוקתו.
achos zekukaso. But the that's point number one, the second חידוש chidush
would be to say Leah can just go away without even חליצה,
chalitza, that this really works even on a דאורייתא de-Oraisa level to
make her enough like his wife that Leah is considered to be
a type of אחות אשה achos isha and there's not even a
מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum and she can just walk away. So
there's two questions: can he consummate it with Rachel and does Leah
require חליצה? chalitza? So let's take a look. Okay, this is already
a new type of a question, alright? It's a little it's gonna
be a little bit of a relief. So let's take a look.
Okay, מת אחד מבעלי האחיות, Meis echad mi-ba'alei ha-achayos, ועושה במופנה מאמר,
ve-oseh ba-mufneh ma'amar, ואחר כך מת אחיו השני. ve-achar kach meis achiv
ha-sheni. בית שמאי אומרים אשתו עמו, Beis Shammai omrim: ishto imo, והלזו
תצא משום אחות אשה, ve-halazu taitzei mishum achos isha, and goodbye to
Leah, she's his wife's sister, which basically means go ahead, consummate the
relationship, Leah doesn't need חליצה, chalitza, the מאמר ma'amar is good enough.
Basically בית שמאי Beis Shammai is giving the weight to the מאמר
ma'amar as if they're already fully married even on דאורייתא de-Oraisa level.
Leah doesn't even need חליצה. chalitza. Okay. ובית הלל אומרים, U-Veis Hillel
omrim, now בית הלל Beis Hillel again coming out לחומרא, le-chumra, מוציא
את אשתו בגט ובחליצה ואשת אחיו בחליצה. motzi es ishto be-get u-ve-chalitza,
ve-eshes achiv be-chalitza. בית הלל Beis Hillel says this is not enough
to do anything. Not only can Leah not leave and he needs
to do חליצה chalitza with Leah, that's one thing, that's saying דאורייתא
de-Oraisa this isn't yet meaningful. But even דרבנן, derabbanan,
even in terms of the אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukaso, we won't let
him consummate it. We say now that Leah is here, she's enough
זקוקתו, zekukaso, even though he's already done this with Rachel, and now
he can't consummate it with Rachel because she's now אחות זקוקתו. achos
zekukaso. So you know what he's got to do? He's got to
do חליצה chalitza with Leah, which fine, makes sense, and he's got
to also do חליצה, chalitza, גט, get, you know, divorce his relationship
with Rachel because of the מאמר. ma'amar. Once there's a מאמר ma'amar
that needs a גט, get, and because of the זיקה, zika, because
of the דאורייתא de-Oraisa connection, that needs a חליצה. chalitza. And he
has to divorce now not only Leah, as it were, חליצה chalitza
with Leah, but even חליצה chalitza with Rachel.
And just to review, if two sisters fall to you in יבום,
yibbum. they're both prohibited to you.
Yeah, because of אחות זקוקתו. achos zekukaso. No, rabbinically. אחות זקוקתו achos
zekukaso you biblically you could do with one and not the other.
But you could?
Yeah, but the idea of אחות זקוקתו achos zekukaso is a דרבנן.
derabbanan. Okay, so let's just read it, let's just read it and
then take the questions. So בית הלל אומרים מוציא את אשתו, Beis
Hillel omrim: motzi es ishto, Rachel he has to divorce, בגט, be-get,
with a גט get because of the מאמר, ma'amar, that means a
גט, get, ובחליצה u-ve-chalitza because still דאורייתא de-Oraisa he hasn't consummated that,
so חליצה chalitza is still needed for the
זיקה. zika. ואשת אחיו, Ve-eshes achiv, and now Leah, בחליצה. be-chalitza. He
has to divorce her with חליצה. chalitza. זו היא שאמרו, Zu hi
she-amru, and this is what they said, אוי לי על אשתו ואוי
לי על אשת אחיו. oi li al ishto ve-oi li al eshes
achiv. Woe for both Leah and for Rachel, I mean for Rachel
and for Leah, like neither of them, both lose out. According to
בית שמאי Beis Shammai everybody's happy, Leah goes without חליצה chalitza and
they finish their relationship, they consummate their relationship. According to בית הלל
Beis Hillel everything gets ruined. Okay, there was a question.
Yeah. What, we're trying to find the status, the strength of מאמר,
ma'amar, and how can you have it both ways? In the one
case it's not strong enough to prevent the relationship, but still strong
enough to require a גט.
get. Yeah, so the גט get is the it's all דרבנן, derabbanan
right? And it's the rabbinic parallel of the מאמר ma'amar which is
the קידושין kiddushin which is דרבנן. derabbanan Okay, so one would think
if it's strong enough to require
the גט get then at least at a דרבנן derabbanan level, meaning
to the דאורייתא de-Oraisa to say that Leah walks off without חליצה
chalitza maybe not, but I agree with you, at least at a
דרבנן derabbanan level to say it solves the problem of אחות זקוקתו
achos zekukaso totally. So it's really the same way the גמרא Gemara
before said, let a דרבנן derabbanan ערוה solve אחות זקוקתו? achos zekukaso?
No. Let a מאמר ma'amar which is דרבנן de-Rabbanan is almost like
יבום, yibbum let that solve אחות... no. Somehow אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato,
remains this big problem, enduring problem. Yes.
Why does Leah have to be bashur?
It says she's in מופנה. mufneh. Yeah, I know, it's very bizarre
that it's in מופנה. mufneh. Yeah, and דף daf here it says
מופנה, mufneh, could have said it before too. I don't know why
it pointed it out here.
Why did the rabbis institute this sister of a זיקה? zika? What
was the...
Yeah,
so you know, I mean, I think that the point was was
that it starts by giving weight to the concept of זיקה, zika,
that זיקה's zika a quasi-קידושין, kiddushin, and then you just play out
the consequences of that. So if he really was married to one
he couldn't have sex with the other because it would be his
wife's sister. And since זיקה's zika a quasi-קידושין, kiddushin, you know,
this gets to questions of people that want to always assume, I'm
not saying you, but in general, that every דרבנן is addressing some
type of a socio-policy type of an issue, you know? I don't
necessarily I don't buy into that. I think that if they conceptually
understood זיקה zika as a quasi-קידושין kiddushin and that's the biblical mechanism
at play, then they're going to go ahead and give it the
sort of you know the type of consequences that it would have
were it to have really been קידושין. kiddushin. But I would explain
it that way, not in terms of some what prob... you know
like societal issue are they solving.
Somebody else might have a very... very different read, but that's the
way I see the גמרא Gemara working. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this: זו היא למעוטי מאי? Zohi lemautei mai? So when
it says, this is the case they said,
woe to the wife and woe and woe to the brother's wife.
It's actually quite fascinating, even in that phrase אוי לי על אשתו,
Oy li al ishto, they're already calling רחל Rachel. אשתו, ishto. right?
I mean בית שמאי Beit Shammai calls רחל Rachel? אשתו. ishto. I
mean he did קידושין Kiddushin with רחל. Rachel Now it's true that
the קידושין Kiddushin doesn't work because it's דאורייתא de-Oraita that requires יבום
yibbum on a דאורייתא de-Oraita level, but they're still calling her אשתו.
Anyway, זו היא למעוטי מאי? Zohi lemautei mai? למעוטי, Lemautei, what does
it excluding? Meaning הא דרבי יהושע Ha de-Rabbi Yehoshua דלא עבדינן כוותיה,
delo avdinan kevataih, like the position of Rabbi Yehoshua that we don't
go like him and we're not going to worry about where he
also has this idea of אוי לי על אשתו אוי לי על
אשת אחיו Oy li al ishto oy li al eshet achiv on
a different case, and that's case we're not going to פסקן pasken
like Rabbi Yehoshua דלא עבדינן כוותיה delo avdinan kevataih אלא אי כרבן
גמליאל אי כרבי אלעזר ella i ke-Rabban Gamliel i ke-Rabbi Eliezer like
those that argue on Rabbi Yehoshua, either Rabban Gamliel or Rabbi Eliezer,
we won't worry about that till we see it. But what now
you have to know is this phrase of woe to my wife
and woe to my wife's sister, my brother's wife, is applied possibly
in other cases other than this, but this משנה is saying this
is the case that we're worried about that of that that scenario.
Okay, now we're going to focus in on בית שמאי's Beit Shammai
fascinating idea that מאמר maamar really works not only at the rabbinic
level to let him consummate but even at the דאורייתא de-Oraita level
to tell לאה Leah that she can walk off. Okay, אמר רבי
אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, לא תימא מאמר לבית שמאי קונה קניין גמור.
lo teima maamar le-Beit Shammai koneh kinyan gamur. Don't say that מאמר
maamar for בית שמאי Beit Shammai is a complete קניין, kinyan, does
everything like is in the place of יבום. yibbum What would be
the consequence of that? דאי בעי לאפוקי סגי ליה בגיטא. de-i baei
le-appokei sagi leh be-gita. Let's say he wanted to break it off
with רחל. Rachel? Could he just, would he have to do חליצה?
chalitzah? Is מאמר maamar ממש mamash like יבום yibbum for בית שמאי
Beit Shammai or would he have to give a גט get or
would a גט get suffice? You got the idea? When he actually
does יבום yibbum, with רחל Rachel and now he wants to get
divorced, what does he do? He went ahead, forget מאמר. maamar. He
did יבום yibbum. with רחל. Rachel, Now they want to get divorced.
What does he do? What does he have to do to divorce
her? Give her a
גט. get. חליצה's chalitzah only before the marriage has consummated. So now
when בית שמאי Beit Shammai says they're like they're married and לאה
Leah can walk off, so how much are they like they're married?
If he now wants to divorce her, can he just give her
a גט get or does he also have to do חליצה? chalitzah?
So he's saying no no they're not a hundred percent married. They're
enough married for לאה Leah, to walk off and for him to
consummate, but not that חליצה chalitzah is no longer relevant if they
wanted to divorce.
לא תימא, Lo teima, don't say מאמר לבית שמאי קונה קניין גמור
דאי בעי לאפוקי סגי ליה בגיטא maamar le-Beit Shammai koneh kinyan gamur
de-i baei le-appokei sagi leh be-gita that if he wants to divorce
her he would just need a גט. get. אלא מאמר לבית שמאי
אינו קונה אלא לדחות בצרה בלבד. Ella maamar le-Beit Shammai eino koneh
ella lidchot be-tzarah bilvad. מאמר maamar has the effect of pushing לאה
Leah, off, of letting him consummate with רחל Rachel, and of letting
לאה Leah not have to demand חליצה. chalitzah. She's enough at a
דאורייתא de-Oraita level, it's enough a case of like ערווה ervah that
she doesn't require even חליצה. chalitzah. But his relationship with רחל Rachel
has not fully transformed and therefore they, if they were to break
it off now they would still need חליצה. chalitzah. אמר רבי אבין,
Amar Rabbi Avin, אף אנא נמי תנינא, af ana nami tanina, it's
fascinating these middle cases, it's enough to do this but not enough
to completely change the status of רחל Rachel, yet. אמר אבין, Amar
Avin, אף אנא נמי תנינא, af ana nami tanina, we can actually,
we actually have taught that. בית שמאי אומרים Beit Shammai omrim in
the previous משנה, now we're still going back to the previous case
about the four brothers and the two sisters and whatever and it
says if they went ahead and they did יבום yibbum when they
shouldn't have and there was אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato. what does בית
שמאי Beit Shammai say? They say יקיימו. yekayyemu. They say you can
keep the wives after you've done this, if you went ahead in
the case of אחות זקוקתו.
achot zekukato So just to remind you that case or similar, right,
you had ראובן and שמעון Shimon married to רחל Rachel and לאה.
Leah They both die. לוי and יהודה. You have a case of
אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato. here, right? This is the classic אחות זקוקתו.
achot zekukato They're not supposed to do יבום, but they ignored it
and they went ahead and did יבום. And בית שמאי Beit Shammai
says they can remain married. Okay, in that case the אחות זקוקתו
achot zekukato. was דרבנן but they can remain married. So what are
we going to infer from that? יקיימו Yekayyemu in, לכתחילה lechatchila no.
Only בדיעבד be-diavad they can remain married, they weren't supposed to do
it, it was אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. But now I will show
you a way where I've got a solution that according to בית
שמאי Beit Shammai you can do this לכתחילה. lechatchila. How? This is
perfect, listen to how you're going to do this. ואי סלקא דעתך
מאמר לבית שמאי קוני קניין גמור. Ve-ei salka daatach maamar le-Beit Shammai
konei kinyan gamur. If מאמר maamar for בית שמאי Beit Shammai works
completely, so here's my solution. זה יעשה
מאמר. Ze yaaseh maamar. The איסור issur is we're saying don't have
sex with רחל. Rachel, She's אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. Fine, I'll tell
you what, I won't have sex with רחל. Rachel, What I'm going
to do is I'm going to do מאמר maamar with רחל. Rachel,
Nobody told me I couldn't give her קידושין, Kiddushin, you just said
don't have sex with her because it's אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato Okay
fine, so I did מאמר maamar with רחל. Now that I've done
מאמר maamar with רחל, what is she? According to בית שמאי, Beit
Shammai, she's my wife. Now she's my wife, לאה's Leah no longer
my זיקה, zikah, right? Because now לאה's Leah, a total ערווה ervah
to me, right? There's no longer a זיקה zikah to לאה. Leah
Now that she's my wife, now I'll
do
יבום with
רחל. consummate it. Okay, so קונה קנין גמור, koneh kinyan gamur, זה
יעשה מאמר ויקנה ze ya’aseh ma’amar veyikneh וזה יעשה מאמר ויקנה. veze
ya’aseh ma’amar veyikneh. So therefore, it must be that it doesn’t work
100% and therefore there still is some אחות זקוקתו problem. Of course
the גמרא Gemara says, I don't understand, that's true, this solution, this
is a good question either way. The גמרא Gemara says like that,
אלא מאי אית לך למימר. ella mai it lach l'meimar. So the
גמרא Gemara says okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like אלא
מאי. ella mai. So the גמרא says so what do you want
to say? דחויה דחויה גמורה? dechuyah dechuyah gemurah? So you want to
say that the reason, the fact, you know, that that that it
completely pushes לאה Leah, off, that the מאמר ma’amar really completely solidifies
the relationship with רחל? Why does that make it any better? So
זה יעשה מאמר, ze ya’aseh ma’amar, same question, זה יעשה מאמר וידחה
ze ya’aseh ma’amar veyidcheh וזה יעשה מאמר וידחה. veze ya’aseh ma’amar veyidcheh.
This question you asked is good either way, whether this מאמר ma’amar
to רחל does it 100% or 90%. If the question is still
the same, why not do the מאמר ma’amar with רחל? If that's
enough in this case, why not do the מאמר ma’amar to put
לאה Leah off the scene? Whether you say that his relationship with
רחל is 100% and now to divide it they would need a
גט get or it's only 95% and they would still need חליצה,
chalitzah, the question is still here: why not do it here? Do
the relationship with רחל, who cares, 95% or 100%, either way it
should push לאה Leah off and let them consummate, right? People sort
of with me? Okay, so sort of. אלא מאי אית לך למימר,
ella mai it lach l'meimar, מאמר דהיתרא דחי. ma’amar deheiteira dachi. So
okay, you've got your question. Why according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai
did you not solve this by first doing מאמר, ma’amar, getting rid
of לאה, and then doing ייבום? yibbum? The answer must be that
even though מאמר ma’amar here gets rid of לאה, that was only
a מאמר ma’amar that was done legitimately. It was done before לאה
was in the picture. And in that case, once the מאמר ma’amar
was done legitimately, then לאה gets in the picture, she's not relevant.
But here, if it was done after לאה was in the picture,
the מאמר ma’amar there can't go ahead and redefine the relationship once
the זיקה zika is already on the scene. The מאמר ma’amar
was before שמעון Shimon
died?
Yes. Right, but here if it would be after שמעון Shimon died,
it cannot in the face of his relationship to לאה, the מאמר
ma’amar to רחל, if he can't consummate with רחל in this case,
the מאמר ma’amar to רחל, you can't do this trick. Oh, I
can't do ייבום yibbum with רחל but I'll do מאמר ma’amar and
that... if you can't do ייבום, yibbum, the מאמר ma’amar loses its
significance. Okay? אלא מאי אית לך למימר, ella mai it lach l'meimar,
מאמר דהיתרא דחי. ma’amar deheiteira dachi. So what do you clearly have
to say? When the מאמר ma’amar was done permissibly before שמעון Shimon
died, then לאה gets pushed away once שמעון died, because then it
was like a קידושין kiddushin where it was like they consummated it.
מאמר דאיסורא לא דחי. ma’amar de'issura lo dachi. If it was done
once he had a זיקה zika to לאה, לא דחי, lo dachi,
it doesn't push off. So that you have to say even if
מאמר ma’amar does a 100%. So
הכא נמי, hacha nami, מאמר אפילו למאן דאמר מאמר קונה קנין גמור.
ma’amar afilu leman d'amar ma’amar koneh kinyan gamur. So that's what you
would say when you say מאמר ma’amar is 95%. It's also if
it would be 100%. מאמר דהיתרא קני דאיסורא לא קני. ma’amar deheiteira
kani de'issura lo kani. It'll only work when it's done without a
competing זיקה. zika. So basically there's one question is why did we
not do the מאמר ma’amar here to solve it? And the answer
is the effect of the מאמר ma’amar according to בית שמאי Beit
Shammai is only when it's unproblematic. As soon as there's a זיקה
zika to לאה and you're not allowed to do ייבום yibbum with
רחל, you can't allow the מאמר ma’amar to be meaningful. If you
can't do ייבום yibbum with רחל, the מאמר ma’amar isn't going to
be meaningful. So that's why this case is not relevant, this is
a case of מאמר דהיתרא. ma’amar deheiteira. Okay, but now that we
said it's a case of מאמר דהיתרא, ma’amar deheiteira, we have to
ask the question according to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, without ייבום yibbum
are they 100% married or only 95%? Are they
married enough to keep לאה out of the picture? But if he
wanted to divorce רחל, would it require חליצה chalitzah or only a
גט? get? And that's still the question we have to resolve. What
we resolved is this only works because of this מאמר דהיתרא. ma’amar
deheiteira. But what is the weight of the מאמר, ma’amar, how much
is it, 100% or not? That's going to be debated. So let's
just read one more line to hear another opinion about this and
then we'll pick up with this tomorrow. רב אשי מתני הכי, Rav
Ashi matni hachi, אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, לא תימא מאמר
לבית שמאי דחי דחויה גמורה lo teima ma’amar l'Beit Shammai dachi dechuyah
gemurah וצרת חליצה נמי לא בעיא. vetzarat chalitzah nami lo ba'aya. You
know, I'm going to stop here because it's going to be too
much of a new point. All right, pick up tomorrow.